Guide to the Jewish Labor Committee, Chicago Records WAG.160
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Jewish Labor Committee, Chicago Records
1952-1986
WAG.160
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
3.0 linear feet (3 boxes)
Founded in 1934, the Jewish Labor Committee (JLC) originated in an effort to link the forces of Jewish unions and other labor and Jewish fraternal organizations in the fight against fascism. In an immediate response to the successful organization of the JLC in New York, a Chicago chapter was established. In the post-war years, Chicago initiated the JLC's efforts in support of civil rights, and in the 1970s, much of the JLC's activity was directed in support of Israel and Soviet Jewry. During the 1980s, the Chicago JLC attempted to revitalize their labor-oriented activities. An outgrowth of this effort was the Ethnic Labor Coalition which included: the Coalition of Black Trade Unionists, the Coalition of Labor Working Women, the Hispanic American Labor Council, the Italian-American Labor Council, Labor for Latin American Advancement, and the Polish-American Labor Council.
Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.)--Chicago (IL)
Provenance
The records of the Jewish Labor Committee s Chicago office were donated to the Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives by Stanley Rosen, an executive board member, and N. Sue Weiler, Director of the Jewish Labor Committee, Chicago. The records were received during the summer of 1995 and the fall of 1996.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Founded in 1934, the Jewish Labor Committee (JLC) originated in an effort to link the forces of Jewish unions and other labor and Jewish fraternal organizations in the fight against fascism. Baruch Charney Vladeck, general manager of the Jewish Daily Forward, organized the founding meeting of the JLC on February 25, 1934 in New York City. In an immediate response to the successful organization of the JLC in New York, a Chicago chapter was established. The activities of the JLC were national in scope and thus the Chicago office participated in campaigns and activities inaugurated by the New York headquarters, as well as undertaking locally-based programs. Jacob Siegel, managing editor of the Chicago edition of the Jewish Daily Forward and a leader of the Workmen s Circle, became the first chairman of the Chicago JLC and led the Chicago JLC until his death in 1965. As did Siegel, executive members and field representatives of the Chicago JLC arose from the ranks of trade unions and the Jewish press. Leading members of the Chicago JLC during Siegel s tenure and in the years following included: Morris Bialis (ILGWU), David Schacter (SEIU), and Aaron ("Archie") Aronin (Chicago Forward.)
Efforts to aid Jews and other victims of Nazi domination, as well as to publicize their plight, were the chief activities of the JLC in its early years. To this end, the JLC joined with the American Jewish Congress to organize a boycott of Nazi goods. During the 1930s the JLC made every effort to aid victims of Naism in Europe, through collections of money, food and clothing drives, and assiostance to refugees and exiles. Following the Allied victory, the JLC contributed to the rehabilitation of war-torn Europe by creating schools, clinics and homes for destitute children, and by providing services for Holocaust surivors in displaced persons camps.
The JLC s aim to "impress upon the Jewish masses that they must fight hand in hand with the general forces of democracy" remained the guiding principle of the JLC after the War. During the decades following the War, the JLC worked toward ensuring democratic rights for workers and minorities in the United States.
An interesting period of the Chicago JLC s activity is documented in the correspondence of the 1950s and 1960s. It was during this time that Chicago initiated their efforts in support of civil rights. Notable among the materials from this time period are the reports detailing the annual Labor Conferences on Civil Rights. Sponsored by the Chicago JLC, these conferences brought civil rights leaders and union officials together in a discussion of how equality could be attained. Inaugurated in 1955, the conferences continued to be held until 1982. In the collection is material concerning the Labor Conferences for 1956, 1965, 1967-1974, 1976-1981, and 1986.
Beginning in the 1970s, much of the JLC s activity was directed in support of Israel and Soviet Jewry. Numerous letters of protest regarding the American government s position with regard to these two areas reflect the JLC s lobbying efforts.
During the 1980s the Chicago JLC attempted to spark a revitalization in their labor-oriented activities. Faced by a threatened dismantling of labor rights under the Reagan administration, the JLC sought to strengthen its connections to trade unions. An outgrowth of this effort was the Ethnic Labor Coalition, a coalition created by the Jewish Labor Committee in conjunction with the A. Philip Randolph Institute. The other agencies which formed this coalition were: Coalition of Black Trade Unionists, Coalition of Labor Working Women, Hispanic American Labor Council, Italian-American Labor Council, Labor for Latin American Advancement, and Polish-American Labor Council.
Sources:
Malmgreen, Gail. "Labor and the Holocaust: The Jewish Labor Committee and the Anti-Nazi Struggle." Labor's Heritage, October 1991.
Weiler, N. Sue "Freedom-Equality-Human Dignity-For All: Conferences on Civil Rights, Jewish Labor Committtee." Typescript, n.d. 32pp. (Copy available at the Wagner Labor Archives.)
Scope and Content Note
The collection of records from the Chicago JLC provides limited but pertinent documentation of the Committee's activity from the early 1950s until the present day. Throughout the Chicago JLC s history, leading trade union representatives participated as chairpersons or executive board members of the committee. The researcher will find material concerning the following individuals: Irving Abrams, Workmen s Circle; Morris Bialis, ILGWU; Sol Brandzel, ACTWU; Harold Schwartz, ILGWU; David Schacter, SEIU.
Letters between the JLC and the other constituent parts of the Ethnic Labor Coalition document the response of labor to the political and economic environment of the 1980s. Other items of note are the various brochures produced by the JLC Chicago; a clippings scrapbook covering the years 1952-1953; a card file detailing the constituent organizations of the Chicago JLC as well as contributions by individual members, and a file documenting the "Bicentennial Project," a conference and a series of forums devoted to the history of the Jewish labor movement in Chicago organized by Professor Stanely Rosen in cooperation with the Chicago Labor Education Program, the University of Illinois -Chicago, and Spertus College of Judaica.
There are 2.5 linear feet of unprocessed materials in box 3.
Arrangement
The files are grouped into 4 series: I, Constitutions, Bylaws, and Executive Board Minutes; II, Scrapbook; III, Correspondence; IV, General Files.
Folders are generally arranged chronologically within each series. The researcher should consult series descriptions for individual series arrangement.
Related Material at the the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Records of the Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.)
The Papers of Jacob Pat (Wagner 127)
Separated Material
A substantial collection of photographs accompanied the Chicago JLC materials and have been transferred to the Wagner Labor Archives Non-Print Collection. The subjects of many of the photos are persons involved with the Labor Conferences on Civil Rights.
Bialis, Morris; Brandzel, Sol; Dubinsky, David, 1892-1982.; Ethnic Labor Coalition.; Held, Adolph, 1885-1969.; Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.).; Schacter, David.; Schwartz, Harold.; Siegel, Jacob.; Vladeck, B. (Baruch), 1886-1938.; Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring.; Anti-fascist movements |z United States.; Chicago (Ill.); Constitutions.; Correspondence.; Financial records.; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945); Jewish labor unions.; Jewish refugees.; Jews |x Persecutions.; Labor unions |z United States; Minutes.; Scrapbooks.; World War, 1939-1945 |x Jews |x Rescue.; World War, 1939-1945 |x Jews.
- Series I: Constitution, Bylaws, and Executive Board Minutes, 1966-1985
  - Constitution and bylaws, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Executive Board Minutes, 1966-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series II: Scrapbook, 1952-1953
  Scope and Contents note
  Details the activities of the Chicago JLC. Includes newspaper clippings and announcements concerning the JLC's Joseph Germano Testimonial Dinner.
  - Scrapbook, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series III: Correspondence, 1953-1992
  Includes incoming and outgoing correspondence as well as reports of Labor Conferences on Civil Rights, and leaflets.
  - Correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1963 Jan-1963 Jun (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1963 Jul-1963 Dec (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1964 Jan-1964 Jun (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1964 Jul-1964 Dec (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1970 Jan-1970 Jun (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1970 Jul-1970 Dec (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 1973 Jan-1973 Jun (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1973 Jul-1973 Dec (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence, 1981 Jan-1981 Jun (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, 1981 Jul-1981 Dec (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence, 1982 Jan-1982 Jun (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence, 1982 Jul-1982 Dec (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence, 1984 Jan-1984 Jun (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1984 Jul-1984 Dec (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1985 Jan-1985 Jun (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1985 Jul-1985 Dec (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1987 Jan-1987 Jun (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1987 Jul-1987 Dec (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1988 Jan-1988 Jun (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1988 Jul-1988 Dec (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1989 Jan-1989 Jun (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1989 Jul-1989 Dec (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Series IV: General Files
  Includes JLC brochures, materials relating to the Ethnic Labor Coalition 1985-1986, and financial and membership records.
  - Bicentennial Project (Chicago Jewish Labor History), 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Ethnic Labor Coalition, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Finances, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Finances, 1977-1980 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Misc. Brochures (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Card File: Membership Data, 1940-1950 (Box 3, Folder 1)